<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<!-- $Revision$ -->

<chapter id="advanced">
    <title> Advanced </title>

    <sect1 id="look-up-tables">
        <title> Look Up Tables </title>

        <para>
            By default, all mathematical functions are calculated and/or
            approximated algorithmicly. In some cases the algorithms use
            a few (static) temporary variables, but generally speaking,
            they don't use large amounts of memory and in most cases they
            are faster than their floating point equivalents.
        </para>

        <para>
            In some cases though, they are not. For example, Athlon CPU's
            "cheat" a little by using a 14-bit look-up table for square
            root calculation and are therefore actually faster! This is
            clearly not what we want.
        </para>

        <para>
            This Fixed Point Math Macro Library also supports look-up table
            variants of all mathematical functions. But considering its
            fields of use, it has to be cache friendly. Large tables would
            ruin the L1 cache. So instead of one large table, I chose to use
            several small tables and linear interpolation for the values
            that don't directly map to the look-up table.
            Depending on the mathematical function that's
            approximated and the precision that's needed, different tables
            are used to accomplish that.
            For example, the square root function needs more
            precision for small values of x, but once the "curve" is mostly
            done, it's almost a straight line and less samples are needed
            to quite accurately approximate the function.
            Depending on the fixed point type chosen and the function at hand,
            two to four tables are needed, each consisting of somewhere around
            128 values. This assures only a few kilobytes of memory and
            hence won't trash the cache in most cases.
        </para>

        <para>
            Look-up tables can be activated by using #define before including
            fixedpointmath.h or by using the -D command line option of your
            compiler. Currently (as of the alpha release) the following
            defines are supported:

            <informaltable>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry> __FPM_ENABLE_ALL_LUT__ </entry>
                            <entry> Enable look-up tables for all
                                    calculations </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> __FPM_ENABLE_SQRT_LUT__ </entry>
                            <entry> Enable look-up tables for all square root
                                    calculations </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> __FPM_ENABLE_EXP_LUT__ </entry>
                            <entry> Enable look-up tables for all exponential
                                    calculations </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry> __FPM_ENABLE_LN_LUT__ </entry>
                            <entry> Enable look-up tables for all natural
                                    logarithm calculations </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </para>

        <para>
            Eventually, all mathematical functions will have their
            look-up table equivalent. I even consider splitting it up for
            every basic fixed point type, which could save memory.
            Embedded systems with only limitted amount of RAM or ROM, could
            benefit from that.
        </para>

        <para>
            Example:

            <programlisting>
        #define __FPM_ENABLE_SQRT_LUT__
        #include &lt;fixedpointmath.h&gt;

        fp16p16_t a, b;

        [...]

        a = sqrtfp16p16(b);     /* will be "looked up" and possibly
                                 * interpolated */ </programlisting>
        </para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="precision">
        <title> Precision </title>

        <para>
            This section will eventually have a whole bunch of graphs that
            show the precision and/or lack thereof of all fixed point
            math macro's compared to 32/64-bit floating point.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="benchmarks">
        <title> Benchmarks </title>

        <para>
            This section (and possibly sub-sections) will have barcharts
            of how the fixed point math routines compare to floating point
            variants on different CPU/FPU's and with different compilers
            and optimization settings.
        </para>

        <para>
            Note: I already noticed that Intel's ICC, in all its wisdom,
            completely optimizes the benchmark program to oblivion, leaving
            only 11 clockcycles (on a Sempron 2400 CPU) for almost all
            timing loops. Something has to be done about that :)
        </para>

        <para>
            This section will also describe how to run benchmarks yourself.
        </para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>

